why is your own voice so enjoy yourself
yes whenever I listen to recordings of
my own voice it's so unfortunate well
it's I mean really you hear yourself
from your own like head poverty right we
are live my friend so uh ladies and
gentlemen welcome to the John Carroll of
podcasts they have Spencer Hicks this is
actually the second time I had on the
podcast but the first time I deleted it
for no apparent reason so Spencer I'm
happy to have you on here man you're
just you're one of my friends who's I
would definitely consider you a very
intellectual person and so you and I
always have very in-depth intelligent
wonderful intriguing growth
conversations where it we learn I feel
like a lot of the we were ended a lot of
the same subjects as well so I'm excited
to have you guys a reoccurring guest on
this podcast
yes it's very it's very nice to be on
here I really enjoy speaking with you
yeah he definitely bring up bringing out
the good and everybody around you man
so um today I think we should just dive
right into like you came in with a
couple things written down in all three
of the words that you wrote down I was
like yes yes yes in those three words
were I would like to define ego
consciousness and mindfulness and were
people to do all those three things so I
would love it if you want to start off
whichever of those three and your
definition I will start with the ego so
people misinterpret the ego as more of
what it's connotated with like I had a
conversation with an older generation
Lee I was like well you just need to
step back and look at your ego a little
bit just like observe it's like well I
don't have an ego okay well not really
not the definition I was looking for so
it prompted me to write down this
question it's really just the the self
that you identify with but it's not
necessarily the true self I would think
that it's and it's different with
everyone you're with as well like you
could be different with other people and
that's just your projection of who you
are right and what you're about
but it's not
certainly you you don't always have to
hold on to it it's a it's a very
abstract concept that's not quite always
easy to grasp but once you get a hold of
it I see it more so so if you were the
media the question that pops into my
mind is ego versus self I mean what it
seems kinda like you're talking about
like this is me like what are you saying
you know the people who are listening
are gonna say you're just talking about
who I say that I am right my name i'm
ashleigh like what what do you mean I'm
Ashley and I'm 14 and I Drive a pink bug
that's me what the self and ego there's
a little bit of a branch there yes so I
would say that the ego is um what you
would most strongly identify as in
general okay so like all these anchoring
physical things like I Drive this this
is what I do like I'm a rapper or this
is my career like these things are
external things then you're anchoring
your yourself too but aren't necessarily
you right yeah I always liked the you
may know this analogy and Sam Harris
used it and I think waking up or one of
his books essentially if you a car if
you take a car and you completely strip
it down completely strip it out every
single part laid out in front of you
like where's the car dis where's the car
there's there's another one it's a few
of a boat and you replace every piece
one of the time until it has all new
pieces is it the same boat yeah exactly
and so we think of you know are our
memories the things that we own the
clothes that we wear we think of that as
that's who we are
but it's it's very hard to define yeah
and I think that's why it's so difficult
to find you go and explain it to people
because it's very much so an extremely
abstract concept but in its it's much
more fluid than people would let on or
that most people think like you feel
like you know this is who I am this is
exactly what I am but it would always be
changing and it's something that
introspection helps you to notice quite
a bit definitely is and I feel like um I
can only do that in silence too because
like a constant noise all the time like
always listening to something I never
actually get interact with it or myself
I'm just kind of careening through my
day yeah what so what do you do do you
are you talking like meditation this
helps you even get going check even just
driving with no music just if you're in
a headspace to take inventory I guess
have your own mental processes like that
just like that little chatter will keep
you away from you digging into this and
I feel like that's why we're so far
removed from seeing it because it's so
easy to be stimulated yeah and I notice
it sometimes too because I'm always
listening to stuff like podcasts music
yeah you know I can't even think a walk
to the next room sometimes days it's so
unfortunate because like it my phone
dies to write aside hey I'm gonna drive
to work no music today like the amount
it's almost like 10 up like what is what
has been holding back like all the stuff
that it's been weighing like on me
just is it's kind of released over 20
minutes and like wow I mean I just got
me and I think about and if I did this
for more than 20 minutes like if I just
didn't have any stimulus for today how
much would I mentally get done like how
much what I figure out about myself if I
wasn't always distracted right I think
that that what happens though is is the
the barrier that our ego creates kind of
when silence happens when there's
silence the barrier that our ego is
creating like reaffirming who we think
we are through our phone or through our
distractions whatever breaks down it's
like silence is like okay well now it's
time to bring these things up but let's
picture reality here well and I'd ripped
it off a little bit so back to the ego I
really it like instagrams a very good
representation of I I preferred saying
avatar than eCos a little easier to
grasp I mean at least for me like this
person that you are on the Internet
that's a definitely a form of you go
like you're projecting this like this is
who I am this is my avatar this would I
want you to see me but it's very curated
and it's really never how people are
yeah it's it's not right it's who we
think we're well it's it's who we think
other people think that we are so we're
dance
yeah we're dancing so so the thing about
ego though is is it starts for me it
seems like in time I talk about it with
somebody who doesn't fully understand
which you know me two years ago I feel
like I didn't understand the word ego
fully and I you know I thought that I
did but there's an offensiveness
to it so I feel like when you say like
oh your ego or the there seems to be
this ownership your ego that people it's
silly because when they get offended if
you say ego or someone stops listening
when you see using the word ego or bring
it up it's their ego that is putting
that structure out so so everybody has
an ego Spencer and is it I feel like
I've read about it being kind of a
primitive so it's something that's left
over from evolution right something to
keep us safe does that make any sense to
you it's definitely a defense mechanism
to some degree especially though like
the incessant guarding of it like being
able we as humans really just don't like
change
and it's the ego can be incredibly fluid
if we allow it to be you can be
essentially whatever you would like to
be and whatever you want to project but
it's very scary to do that and to let go
of like who you are these things that
define you them because now it's even if
these things are harmful to you thinking
about being someone else doing something
else is very hard I mean you hear people
all the time say well like I can't quit
my job and go do this thing like why
can't you like why can't you be someone
new yeah so I feel like as a society
it's extremely frowned upon to change in
general which i think is a big cause of
the problem yeah we're kind of always
taught that we're born to be who we are
you know like and it's like oh my
problems I got to deal with them so
everybody's got to deal with them it's
kind of locks in who we think we are and
I think the social connotation to the
literal world ego
is pretty rough to like you mentioned
earlier just because it's it's
connotated in a very poor light usually
thank you oh you've got a big ego yeah
it kinda I feel like when I hear the
word ego I picture some like some cocky
dude right I think that was my own
that's how I always used to think
authority go I'm some dude who talks
about himself too much I'm like oh he's
egotistical or oh he's he's got a big
ego I mean that's I mean that whole
phrasing of how he used to how I used to
use the word ego is just entirely
incorrect it doesn't it doesn't grasp or
explain what it is at all it's very ego
is I think every single human on earth
needs to understand ego ego is something
that is very gripping to a lot of us and
just to participate in society and
culture of today your ego is something
that you have to have like it's it's you
have to have it in check to be
successful I think to be forgiving and
not get caught up in every single every
single Kalp [__] that you step it and
every single little argument that
someone is challenging who they who you
think you are yeah I think that ego is
one of the most important things to
fully grasp I think that even you know
if you gain if listeners if you gain in
some sort of insightfulness from just
listening to us talk about a you go I
really encourage you to dive further
into the word ego there's plenty of
YouTube videos plenty of searching the
word what is searching what is ego on
Google the first thing that comes up is
just wonderful I for sure I remember
doing it so yeah man so ego is is is
kind of quite a crazy thing I think how
have you besides silence Spencer how
have you navigated your ego like as you
understand the concept of the word as
you understand yours the people around
you how do you navigate ego I mean it
really starts with I mean we're gonna
get to another word but a mindfulness
practice or a meditation because in
order to I can change behavior you must
notice it first right and if you never
get to the point of noticing it
it's just moved like that's not it's not
even on your radar
so just um when I'm navigating my daily
life I mean a lot of time it's in
hindsight as well this is just very easy
to just instinctively react to things
and and just uh no no be who you are in
quotes I guess but I will catch myself
at the end of the day thinking about
just the actions not in like a poor life
but just like how how did this affect me
throughout the day and like how did it
change my social interactions right yeah
I mean it's really good to be
introspective at the end of the day I
think that's where I find myself I used
to I mean I used to just not have a
handle on my depression all and so I
would be introspective about my day
right at the end of the day and I'd be
like dude you suck this you suck at this
but it was you know it was the real me
disagreeing with like what my ego self
was doing out in the real world or or
you know saying or talking about like
things that I'm just like huh I didn't
really want to act that particular way
or whatever it may be I think a lot of
like depression what not really comes
from not I mean the true self is like a
big ideological concept that might not
even be a real thing but like acting in
a way that doesn't abide by that and
then like you said realizing that is
young it's going to make you upset and
it's something like primal internal
degree like you're just not the way you
navigate yourself with other people is
just not in tune with who you are though
like the frequency you give but being
aware of it and being introspective and
just you know whether it's taken the end
of your night whether it's meditating
wherever you can fit it in what
meditation does is it puts a little
wedge in between to where when
situations happen you could be like no I
don't want to act that way or oh my mind
is my mind is thinking like crazy and I
just noticed that it was mindfulness
teaches you that's go for sure so let's
actually talk about mindfulness - yes so
you give me your definition of mop well
let's Jake
at all times we're thinking at all times
there's a million thoughts going through
our minds noting knowing that and
noticing that our two things that are
profound once you realize that you can
do that
I went 26 years of my life without
really having mindfulness knowing that
at all times my mind is going a million
miles a minute I thought that whatever
word whatever feeling whatever blah blah
blah
comes in that that's what happens but
being mindful of I guess the fact that
I'm thinking all the times is
mindfulness at the root for me what do
you think about that definition I like
it a lot I mean I really like to look at
like a third point perspective like a
third-person perspective on yourself so
like in accordance to your thoughts so
you don't really get to choose what you
think but you definitely need to choose
what you hang on to and mindfulness like
you said just puts that wedge in there
and you you instead of like that
guttural instinct reaction to something
and then following it like anger is an
easy one to pick on because it's so like
volatile and very easy to like see like
this this was not a feeling that you
chose to feel but it's a feeling that
you chose to feed so if you've you're
mindful you can realize that you just
fed that instead of just feeding it and
asking for forgiveness later and then
also on the his same headspace you
really just get a look at way why am i
angry likewise it's upsetting to me do I
have am i rightfully angry or am i angry
because I'm protecting my Who I am my
ego which can be very fragile and it's
very easy to somebody to say something's
off putting to you and it's usually
something that's probably critical when
you probably need to hear usually the
things we get really mad about or
usually stuff yeah we're trying to
protect ourselves from pain at all times
right in our minds our brain is trying
to protect ourselves so it doesn't want
us to hurt if we accept those things
about ourselves so we really live those
true meet beings a lot of times that
hurts
and so our ego is projecting out kind of
the opposite or we're like defending
like of course I'm not like that because
if you were like that it would hurt a
lot and so your ego is like almost
a little scorpion tail it's always
working well you're like while you're
looking down there's a scorpion tails
that snap in people get sure they don't
hurt you and I really think uh like this
with realizing the ego also helps you
did not feel so bad when you introspect
you're mindful of yourself you're like
wow this is really really not acceptable
behavior nice like usually if you if
you've got a very strong sense of self
that's gonna feel really bad because
it's like it's an attack on your
identity but if you can like hey I'm not
the person that I think I am I'm like
this fluid being and then you react in a
certain way or something is very
off-putting or upsetting to you mm-hmm
instead of instead of the guard you to
look at why like why am I upset about
this why did this why's is off-putting
to me and then stead of being like a
beat up by the fact that you got upset
by it you not can really realize okay
this is how I'm gonna do better like
this is this is the thought process that
got me here and this is why it's
unacceptable but I'm okay with that
exactly I mean not isn't like a
contentment but it's a I'm not gonna
beat myself up over it aside yet I do
see a lot of people that they're like
anxious or depressed or have like pretty
deep-seated issues and if they just
start like digging through that it just
feels bad and we will always try to
avoid pain like all your biology is set
up to just avoid paying our society is
set up to opinion yeah the blog of
happiness so I've actually done recent
research and it used to be pursuit of
pleasure pleasure and avoidance of pain
and it's actually just avoidance of pain
like that's a one thing that you do like
pleasure is a part of that yeah because
it's the opposite but it is 100 percent
mmm almost all of your decisions or to
avoid well it's funny you can narrow all
you can follow all like pain annoyance
boredom it all goes back to let's say
fear right I mean it's these emotions
and it's I feel like when you just
follow it back like of course I don't
want to feel this because at my core
being all I want is the best for myself
like I I don't want to get mad and ruin
my life because I yelled at someone like
why would I want that I want the best
for myself
so we have a lot of you know I guess
posturing that's a very good words yeah
it's yeah our society is just so full of
posturing it's funny I said I always try
not to use the word society and culture
alert because I just feel like people
are in a widget a tinfoil hat on my head
but I don't know I think that it is I
mean why else are we having this
conversation right it's something that's
important for our our culture our
society to know right now and be aware
of because I you know I I'm victim to it
myself I have an ego I haven't always
been mindful I can always be more
mindful some days if I miss my morning
meditation I'm like great I mean it's
mindful today maybe I'm gonna let my
emotions get the best of me like and of
course I don't want that so it just
happens to everybody we got to work on
it and I feel like it's very much so
it's such a Western problem it's like
Buddhism and Hinduism I mean I don't
agree with Hinduism like that like the
overarching structure of it yeah but in
Eastern culture the emphasis on
introspection is very much so held to a
high degree and we in the West not so
much like whenever you speak to old
people especially their like their sense
of self and their egos is just so stout
mm-hm it's so incredibly inflexible and
you notice it I mean in their political
views like they're just are so unwilling
to change and it's um it's actually very
unfortunate to see people that are very
old that live their whole lives and
never been able to like break the mold
like who I am right yeah well I think
that what's happening though is we've
had you know the two generations like
that are happening you know at the boot
of technology like what's happening is
this huge separation between these two
generations who have like we love
technology like let's say us and I know
us being like the top of the younger
people and then the people were like
four years older than us who also kind
of got technology too right like the
separation between our three generations
and old people say 60 years old who are
definitive in their ways very political
that separation because of the the
technology is like this very apparent
and what's what's really putting a wedge
between that the conversation that needs
to be happening that's like an open
conversation where it can actually talk
to each other is the ego and it's weird
because it seems like it's it's the ego
old people have a huge ego but also
there's young people who are doing what
we're doing very wrong there's a young
young people who are also having huge
egos who are are thinking like they're
just throwing away every single thing
little people say just because they have
a posturing you know let's dance
against these people so there's two
different versions of ego with three
different generations that are going to
head-to-head and it's just weird it's
funny because what old people told us
the internet would do to our brains it
did to them they just they will believe
everything because it's like oh it's
gonna melt your brain like you're gonna
believe all these crazy things like they
have incredibly poor opinions because
they can't censor egay because they've
been they just haven't taken so little
information compared to us and they
haven't live in a world where they have
like a massive distrust or like a
government and establishment so they're
very much so very status quo - so it's
like it is so we're so polar opposites
but I really tried to not I trying to
not be upset a device ever like young
team team young people it's like I
generally feel very bad for these people
no it's terrible I I think well I mean
you and I were talking about this even
before the podcast is the nature of our
being whether we want it to be or not I
think is a bit of an advocate a bit of a
moderator a bit of a you know if there's
two people arguing who clearly are just
misunderstanding each other's opinion or
what the essence of what they mean is we
are the type to try to be like oh no no
just listen here's what you mean here's
what you mean now have a conversation so
I think that you know I guess yeah you
us having these conversations is it's
important a definition of terms and
that's why I wanted to start with that -
is the definition terms is so incredibly
important when you're speaking about
things because two people can be arguing
the same point with different terms and
be upset at each other absolutely that
is not very helpful it's so foolish it
seems like and now that I think the more
that I learn and the more that I can
really
see it the more that I sharpened that
tool of this skill like watching like Oh
what does this person really mean and
really trying to understand people you
see it man it's like it's the essence of
like most problems and again ego is what
is just guarding us from just letting go
and be like hey listen what the [__] to
you just let me listen to you for an
hour what do you really mean here
because if you just let someone talk if
you get rid of your posturing your
stance your ego and you just learn from
someone talking you actually start to
see things eye-to-eye and realize you're
talking about a lot the same things and
sometimes I mean you see a lot of
political problems and like there's
always give you have a hard political
leaning the other side is gonna complain
about stuff and it's probably the same
problems you have it's just framed
differently incredibly differently like
they just have a wrong scapegoat for it
that isn't yours so it's like we are all
people together that have to live in
this in a society like these are not
like the reason that life is hard is not
these old people like okay boomer is
really funny like I think okay boomer is
one of the funny things wrong but it's
super not helpful because it causes
divisive nosara inherent problem like
they're your grandparents they're
another problem like that we have
systemic issues that they didn't cause
like they have to deal with all the same
[__] that you do so they're they're just
I mean their kin they're kind of thrown
into this [__] just as we are I think
that we're like don't you understand
that this is not real and they're like
we don't know what else to do either so
we're just gonna stand here with our
thing one how can you ever expect them
to just adapt adapt to instead of so
I've read a statistic and it's like our
grandparents or people above the age of
80 we've taken in more information by 25
years than they did for like 70 years I
think they can adapt to that it's so
incredible it's overwhelming for me and
I am I try to read as much as possible
and taking a lot information it's
overwhelming so I can't imagine how
these people feel on their age when
they're not adapted to this well they're
gonna feel like their usefulness has
been kind of dried up right like you
don't call your grandma
to like hey what's the recipe for this
you just look it up online and there's
probably a better recipe than your
grandma gave you nowadays
that's a weird how do we cope with [__]
like that and I'm hard-pressed to say
that their wisdom it's actually just
it's it's not it's not the best because
we have the internet and people they
grew up in a society that didn't value
introspection or any of these things and
then not no fault of their own it's just
not part of the culture here and they've
just been fed like one news source like
all this information and force-fed to
them and they've just been like this
well they got there's no other objective
reality for them so even their wisdom is
just not as helpful now so the one thing
you're supposed to have when your role
this must be old wise man which I think
being aged and being wise are two
different things but the stereotypical
person is wise of course and the
Internet has profound amounts of wisdom
that they have kid barely like grass
some of them this is a very large
blanket statement but no Michael horse
Utley soon yeah a lot of the whole
people are run into I feel like that
that probably feels really bad like the
one thing mm-hmm
because old wise man teach teach my kids
all this stuff it's like it'd be
wonderful to have that the internet just
does it so much better yeah I mean you
read all these books you know and then
you discover that like reading three
books you pretty much get the
summarizations of that by one
sixteen-year-old kid watching a
documentary on Netflix like well those
three books took me four weeks and that
took him four d four minutes so I mean
not that it's the exact same information
but I was just thinking of a of an
analogy like because I can't say that
where you and I get our information
where we get our truth where we get our
news is perfectly more truthful and more
reliable than where they get theirs but
we also do and know a thing or two we
know like a lot of the news networks
that I mean the news that is you know
Fox News CBS I I don't really even know
any of these I'm not saying pinpointing
exactly but it's fed one wormhole of of
information like this is what you care
about at all times and now there's
24-hour news there's something that's
breaking there's something that's
worth watching at all times so I was
thinking when we say like hey this isn't
the only truth like when we're trying to
explain to old people who are you know
watching the same news stations as they
have been for 25 years saying like hey
this is biased this isn't the whole
picture there's a whole world this
whatever whatever imagine if we walked
in when there was only TVs before the
internet and we walked into someone's
home they're sitting around family
dinner six of them and you're like hey
what you're watching on this TV right
now I know that that's the president but
that's false
that is wrong he's lying it's not true
they'd be like what the [__] are you
talking about of course this is true
this is the most true thing ever so the
way that we get our truth in this world
has been completely compromised and old
people there's no anything cope with
that that's on they just have not been I
mean the blanket statement yeah being
skeptical is a it's a skill you gotta
work up you don't just like all of a
sudden don't believe anything right and
these people didn't have to do it like
why would the news lie like there's a
very much so a systemic I mean all the
news is set up to just piss them off and
cause divisive news and I think that's
why okay boomer is funny but also
upsetting because we're just adding to
that what's the okay boomer okay okay so
okay boomer is like that come back for
when old people say like ridiculous
stuff or like they have just terrible
political opinions like it's a big name
you know okay boomer like this is like
the Stonewall Forum in it's like going
over right now which is funny it's
objectively pretty funny but it's
deadlies it's great we can't be upset of
those people like we have to have
incredible empathy for people to like
what are we saying like our opinions is
because we're like I'm no important no
more important than other humans like
we're all living here we have to figure
out how we can I just think that the
device in is a problem and I actually
wanted to go over us versus them yeah us
versus them mentality is not like that
it's just incredibly I mean that's a one
of the biggest ones I see is young
people versus old people especially
because the political sphere is getting
very heated right now because the
elections coming out like there's so
much divisive NISS and there's a lot of
like corporate energy entities that make
a lot of money from
divisive nests mm-hmm so when we just
like eat that all day it's very easy to
be angry like oh those are the other
guys like it's like the caveman brain
just wants the enemy right they want
like an actual eyes like this person's
the problem their opinions are bad and
I'm going to do everything against this
person we have justice because we can
once we get that person we can make them
feel bad and so we just got a rise above
that I really really try to not do that
it's extremely hard because I really
think the whole people have terrible
opinions I really disagree with almost
everything they believe in but I can't
they can't let that dictate how I treat
individual people yeah I mean that's
that's an us-versus-them right things
like the self is extremely important and
when you're in groups like that
groupthink and that big like I feel good
I got my tribe behind me all these
people we all like hate is so much more
rallying than love it's easier and like
the corporatism especially in like
Western culture really really sells that
to everyone us versus them is sold to us
every single day I feel super bad I was
it's funny it's this left you know it
does say politics is a great example red
and wine door left and right it's like
you don't have to choose one of them you
don't have to talk about a person as if
that summarizes exactly where they are
in their entire being because that
creates right away that even our
political system and its core creates an
us-versus-them conversation and so I was
thinking though so like we're having
conversation were saying oh we're young
people and they're old people I also
think that there's a nervousness there's
a weirdness in like the Western cultural
language where us versus them is even
kind of a weirdo thing to talk about
when I so I was just thinking about race
so if I'm saying talking about a black
man like saying black male or saying
like Mexican so like race for example
talking about me versus them like as a
white man saying Mexican or or a black
person that seems weird coming out of my
mouth like it feels like I'm not used to
talking about it
or considering us versus them out loud
conveying differences but we seem so we
like ignore that conversation and we're
like we're all equal in that sense we
don't even talk about like I could we're
just people I'm not black you're not
white we're just people we have that but
then when it comes to political [__]
it's so fast to just it's so comfortable
to say oh you're a left-wing or you're a
right-wing or whatever so our
conversation is so we're down are so
aggravating there are so incredibly
aggravating to talk about because if you
just have strong opinions and somebody
is a divisive Lee opposing you then it's
like this is what I think the good of
all people is gonna be and you have
somebody else who thinks the opposite of
that it's inherently just gonna cause
some friction right and then it's just
you get the mob mentality then you go
find spaces where there echo chambers
and people only believe what you believe
and these ideas proliferate they get
more radical more radical and then you
have like two entities of people that
could not be more diametrically opposed
yeah who are there solidified in a
belief I believe this you guys believe
this we are that
but then it's like in 10 years like what
are you still that like if you look back
and I go what was I doing exactly 10
years ago on this day I could just stop
and think about yourself at that moment
cuz you're gonna be like oh I was
representing that entire thing saying
that was my entire being that's my whole
that's who I am that's what I'm gonna
fight against the opposite of and this
really goes back to the ego as well
because I mean you see it a lot in like
I mean sell a tree of all kinds but
especially religious zealotry because
it's a belief that you've attached to
yourself and now anybody that's refuting
it is attacking you and not a concept
right and that's very like people are
dangerous yes it's really dangerous and
if you can not identify with that a
personal level and like as a concept
it's very helpful like because then when
you're it's you don't get like that ape
reaction to like oh there this is who I
am they're attacking my beliefs he's
like they're defensive they're taking an
idea and I've gotten a lot of mileage
out of not telling people which way I
lean in just talking about ideas and
concepts
hey this is this is the problem we're
like policy I guess this is the problem
let's converse about it and I won't tell
people hi lien and that you will get so
much further with people if you can like
just do that right I I think so I
definitely agree with that but I also
think that it's has become okay to be in
a constant state of contempt and say
that that's a personality and so a lot
of times like oh I'm so open to your
opinion right and then as you're talking
I'm like mmhmm mmhmm I'm making faces
I'm doing like that though again
politics Donald Trump does that like
like the weird like oh I'm not believing
what you're saying you're not actually
listening you're solidifying I am this
stance against your stance and so we
can't get anywhere from that so I mean
even just listening the US versus them
requires you to dissolve that requires
everyone to be a better listener and
being a better listener means your body
language your face you're like just
listen and let them talk to that that's
another huge thing I do want to I do
want to really the just the US versus
them thing like that what so what how
would you define I guess just even that
sense us versus them because I think
it's a huge thing that we should
definitely know it helps a lot of our
conversations I think it's really just
like that it's just a classic tribalism
you know like it goes back to those
caveman days when people that don't look
like you from another tribe they're like
come to kill you tickler stuff like we
just haven't we've ideologically and
technologically grown so fast but we
haven't shaken like how like your
humanity and what we once were so trying
to navigate that on like myself from
SPRO yeah it's very hard to be passive
fires as he as he texted me this morning
phones are the great pacifier people so
versus that when when we're having these
conversations so how do we when people
are listening because you know even
listening so say are this the previous
part of the conversation
my old people if I was an older person I
would be like wouldn't you don't know
whatever like you're talking about me
like whatever you you start to get a
stance instead of just listening and
trying to let them explain so dissolving
the us first them mentality I mean how
mindfulness again I guess I think it
really comes down to humanizing people
true it's so easy to dehumanize somebody
that doesn't believe what you believe to
like a very extreme degree mm-hmm it's
like oh and then you label them like the
the caveman brain and it's actually very
novel and good that we're extremely good
at categorizing things like as humans
like you I mean it's just how he says
that's how we survived like you see a
snake some snakes are poisonous so this
snake is poisonous or venomous rather
and you just believe that so you put
things in boxes and you can pump analyze
them we start doing that to people it
does not lead to very helpful
conversation mm-hm and just looking at
people like like from where they're
coming from I guess like meeting people
where they're at essentially because
there's a reason they're upset mm-hmm
and it's probably not what they're
talking about
like they somebody either fed this to
them as a solution to a problem they
have that you also probably have like
trying to understand the root of
someone's pain will help a lot in this
yeah go ahead and that requires a very
very large deal of empathy and it's also
hard to give that to people you disagree
with and but these are a tough one
though because I think that you know the
news the world of news is also empathy
is a weird thing I think we
misunderstand empathy and sympathy
feeling other people's pain is not super
healthy all the time because then it
gets us like it makes us pick up this
pitchfork like I will avenge you sort of
gives it the kind of hits that core of
our being so being empathetic is super
we can talk about that in another
podcast but I yeah but but so sympathy
want one thing that I do for that is
like how I'm able to be empathetic
towards everyone I feel
in my meditations I always think of
people throughout their whole life so I
was like okay I'm say the subject is
someone that you've had a disagreement
with and so I bring that person to mine
and I think about them five years ago
like what were they doing on you know
maybe they were just getting their
license maybe they were a young kid then
ten years ago oh they were a teenager oh
they were a kid you think of someone as
a whole being you know they've had a
whole life they have a mother there's
these things that they're trying to
protect
right they have a family at home when
their argument with you is just trying
to make sure that [__] doesn't go
straight right like the essence of them
is to just stay safe just like it is for
you and so I think for me like in
meditations and then just kind of think
about it once in a while when you have
an argument or talking to somebody like
man this [__] has had a whole
life they fit a baby they were a baby
that's who they were they were a baby
they got a mom I really uh so there's a
full ideal I'd you earn a philosophy
called determinism and it's basically
predicated upon the fact that uh okay so
the universe explodes and everything
from then hasn't led to you where you're
at now and you haven't got to chose
choose any of that so if it's like
nature versus nurture like that's what
people say like that's the argument you
don't really get to choose either of
those things and you will instinctively
react to your environment anyways so you
you haven't got to really choose who you
are and how you got to where you are
it's just like almost by happenstance
right so looking at other people like if
I was this person I would be exactly the
same way exactly his is incredibly
humanizing and it's it for me has led to
a very large degree of empathy just for
everyone even people that I'd like you
can't even fathom how they came to
conclusion they did or the way that they
are the way they are but then thinking I
mean I would be the same way if I was
them yeah like you know you're gonna
have that instant so that's the thing as
so mindfulness puts a wedge in that
instant reaction so what we're talking
about here is everybody has these
reactions of like
you're an absolute idiot what are you
talking about we're like this you
immediately compartmentalize someone
into them they know less than I do they
know they're wrong but at the essence of
what's going on that you're just
misunderstanding each other so when you
can see someone as a whole being and you
can practice mindfulness to put the
wedge in and be like okay I can feel
this anxiety raising up I can feel this
anger raising up I'm not gonna let that
anger control what's coming out of my
mouth I'm gonna stop and listen to them
let them talk I'm gonna I'm gonna I'm
gonna wait for them to explain what they
really mean not just the words that
they're saying and intent is incredibly
important and we lose that a lot I
really think because the ego like you
you want to get the equipment like you
want to own this guy that you feel so
good doesn't it oh you're wrong I'm
right and it's just is so reassuring but
that is not helpful rhetoric and it's
not helpful for anyone involved it just
usually if you want if you want to
change someone opinion you can't do that
like because they will always double
down every single time to protect their
own ego so you would just I mean I would
do the exact same thing so if you can
facilitate people to just kind of leech
it out of them like get them to explain
themselves even if even wouldn't if
they're done you really still don't
disagree with them at least you can now
have a more open dialogue and maybe
changing their mind because the moment
you get on that back foot the front of
your brain that does a lot of cognitive
reasoning shuts off and just the stem
will fire and that's just caveman
protection instincts right so if you can
keep people from like that
fight-or-flight response when you're
talking to them you'll get a lot further
mm-hmm and noticing when you've locked
into that same response you're if you're
being defensive yourself just I love
being upset I do I love being
politically outraged especially right
afterwards you don't you own someone an
argument you like I felt good I've been
really been trying to get away from
doing it because it it does feel great
like it's it's a hard not to you
something [__] helpful it's so not
helpful and when you look at like we're
all in this
together like witness we all got a
navigate life like this person is trying
their best I'm sure
they have probably very similar problems
to me right it's just not helpful
discourse and it will further divide
people and not doing that is extremely
helpful mm-hmm yeah that's all super
important man I'm glad that we can kind
of summarize things and hopefully you
know that that's certainly what I want
to be doing over time this is defining
things a little better in allowing
people to to slow down and and you know
because because a lot of what we're
having trouble doing in our
conversations in today's world is is
even getting to the conversation because
we even we hit these barriers of like
the oh you're wearing a red hat with
that while riding on it like I'm not
even gonna let you speak but it's just
stopping things so explaining things and
really helping us see each other as
humans and just humanizing conversation
to where we can actually talk to each
other and realize like yeah we're vastly
different we think way different things
but we're also with you hurling through
[__] space on this big ol rock dude
once once you really think about the
absurdity of this existing it's like
boils everything down to just me it's
just like such a non-issue feeling like
we're spinning around a stone that's
hurling through the universe mm-hmm with
a galaxy that's also hurtling through
the universe and like this petty
argument it just is so not important
mm-hmm in its you know it's at the end
of even just your small short life you
know each of us we're going to there
will be even the same laughing moment
right like oh man that was so petty
you're not gonna kind of think goodness
I own that mo [__] leftist in that
argument when I was 28 I mean just
what's important to you you know a bunch
of stuff oh the phones are the greater
dual pacifier oh I definitely want to
dip into that what is your to see text
me that this morning
I think of that too it's funny this
podcast I feel like a lot of my episodes
have been just like social media sucks
and phones are evil and all this stuff
like I mean I'm addicted to all these
things too and I have my ways of of
branching with them as well but so
explain to me how my phone is a pacifier
okay well if you anyone goes to dinner
in the u.s. you see everyone on their
phone mm-hmm and another thing we didn't
touch on with meditation is it just
cause you to be present and the phone is
the opposite of being present and I've
noticed that it's really it detracted
for my life and relationships and it's
led me with and the dopamine tick is so
important I get so bored so fast from
being so stimulated that I can't enjoy
stuff ever I can't enjoy mottely it's
extremely extremely hard to enjoy just
my everyday moments because I'm so used
to just being blasted with information I
know I mean it's it's we're constantly
we have everything we ever want and then
that's the truth of life though is
everything ever want is never enough so
so the present moment certainly pulls us
away or the phone pulls us away from the
present moment what you wanted to find
the present moment let's make sure
that's clear yeah it really is I mean
it's quite literally now and you can let
it slip very easily by not paying
attention to it or not being mindful of
it mm-hmm like when you sit on Instagram
and like sometimes gramma just look at
[__] posts look at memes and just like
in take a little laughs you get a little
dopamine hit every time you click but
it's not actually satisfying
it's just pacifying like this is not
when I have this realization so I was
almost YouTube for like five hours a day
like in taking helpful information but
it's still it's just way too much
information to me and I will find myself
down the down the rabbit hole
just watching soap water stuff and then
I like set my phone I'm like what do I
really care about like what like what
what would I be doing right now if I
wasn't doing this there's definitely
something that is more constructive
because YouTube didn't just throw me
down this what would I care about yeah
like I there's things that I do that
bring me much more joy than this and I'm
choosing to do this right now and I
chooses to do this
a lot I feel like others do as well and
it really detracts from all right
but it put you pulls you out of the
present moment I mean but that's the
thing as a lot of times you're you're
learning you know
well you're enjoying like of course I'm
pulled out the present moment I'm
enjoying my life I'm enjoying this thing
like so so why would the why is the
present moment even important than
Spencer if if we're just feeling better
when we're doing six hours of YouTube
because ultimately not constructive at
to a point yes seek your knowledge learn
new things but there's a point of over
stimulation and what you just cannot
take anything else and I find myself in
this abilities quite a bit or I've just
very much so over blasted with
information and it's like the little
stuff like like if you're watching
YouTube and around your door like that
sweet like decaying fall smell of all
the dead leaves like there's so many
things that are beautiful on mundane the
100% look over you never gonna get back
just because you're staring on your
phone right you know so but that's funny
the you know this smell of the leaves
even that so that's something I think
that our ego helps us say like oh I'm
just not into that sort of thing right
like you say like oh I'm not I'm not a
fall person or I'm not I don't like the
outside or blah blah blah but these are
like naturally healing I think these are
just being a human it's it's important
to connect these things we get you know
oxygen and breath from from the outside
from the trees the the being pulled
constantly out of the present moment
seems so you know doesn't seem like a
big deal when this is better I'm holding
up my phone here holding up my phone is
better than reality right like so if
your life sucks at home the present
moment isn't is it nice
this is a nice thing to escape from
right but I think we're a little
confused about what the present that the
present is like we think of it like hear
what the here's my reality not not
slowing down and being like
really breaking apart what it smells
like in this room you know what it what
are the intricacies of how things feel
and in using our senses to really
breathe in and stop and slow down and
stop thinking so much and read that in
and that's really a core tenet of
meditation as well it's just like
anchoring the five senses and just
taking note of sensory input I don't
know if that's how you meditate but yeah
a lot of the time I really admire table
eyes open
mm-hmm cuz it's just this is nice a lot
of people have good success with eyes
open I'm not someone who has slit eyes
open but a ton of people that you do
very well with eyes open that patient I
got to be really on top of meditating
every day till I can get to the point
where it's productive because I mean you
get the twitch pick up your phone
do it like anything these little obtrude
ins under your consciousness you're like
your stream of reality and they just
make you want to not do what you're
doing like there's something so
uncomfortable about doing nothing and I
feel like the old iPhone is a big part
of that the old pacifier and I mean
that's really one of this he mean you
see like kids not being parented like
even I am criminally under present my
like relationship like my love
relationship all right all right and
just because I mean once you get really
comfortable people when you see it at
dinner tables you just well I know I
know how they feel we talked about all
the things but but so that's the thing
is to search for the present moment and
make sure you're always in the present
so I have that same thing because I used
to be on my phone so much more often
than I am now and I'll have moments
where I'm like shaven I'll both be on
her phone for like let's say a minute at
dinner yesterday literally at Applebee's
we were on our phones and I have moments
now because I've kind of trained myself
like oh let's lock back in that present
moment I'll put my phone down and um
I'll just you know try to think of
something like a tie game if a meteor
hit right now babe what would you do
like what do you think would happen and
you know all sudden you have a 20-minute
wonderful conversation you know so
exploring wonder talking about like you
could even be like hey what do you think
like would you ever adopt a kid you know
have those conversations just I think
that we also use the phone for things to
talk
right I mean it's gossip is is man
that's something I'm really trying to
break apart I'm reading a you've all
know her oddities sapiens right now and
he's talking about gossip oh man I'm not
super far into it but it's so good so
it's very good but a gossip me and it's
the phone the the click culture has
fueled our gossip too we're pretty much
there's entire people who they're never
talking about anything other than what's
being regurgitating to them like did you
hear about this did you hear about this
did you about this did you about this
man that's that I feel like that's
almost taking our phone and even though
it's down it's leaving our phone on
because we're not in the present moment
still we're still carrying on this thing
that's that's elsewhere over here but
but anyway yes so I was trying to round
out in your relationship in your like
even our friendships once in a while
dude like you notice like of course we
love being on our phone of course red
it's great YouTube's great Instagram
whatever but once why you gotta be like
let's let's try to be creative here
let's try to explore my [__] life and
not just use the whole thing on my phone
put your phone down look at the person
across to you say what's happening
what's going on
you know like let's talk about something
in depth and I've personally found it so
much more enriching to just have a
conversation because what's on this
what's on this guy it's really just it's
never positive positive new doesn't
doesn't sell oh you're being sold that
you're inadequate people trying to sell
you stuff in the way best way to sell
you stuff is to make you feel like
you're less than currently so I know if
I have this thing I'll be better in all
these sites that's just what they're
doing and all the gossip I mean it's
just programming your brain to also to
want that for your own life
I mean I've recently take naps every
single day and I'll be like watching
YouTube and I'll go to sleep and I'll
have like pretty vivid dreams that are
very very similar to what I was watching
and it's really heartened me to believe
that what you intake like weighs so
heavily on your subconscious right and
if you into
just garbage all the time like he said
she said I call the celebrity gossip
like all this negativity like it really
does affect you even if you don't
realize it like it really changed who
you are and how you react to the world
and what you seek out for pleasures well
absolutely does so if you go have a
really constructive conversation or just
like something fun like something
playful think that's so much more
helpful for you like as a person that's
staring at that screen right
yeah it's it's the the screen the phone
is kind of like that that shortcut to
the the chemical reaction that happens
like so when you if you if you are
unaware listener when you pick up your
phone and you click on something so if
you get the notification ding and you
hear that and you immediately pick up
your phone and you click like alright
got it
that is the chemical dopamine is being
released new bright and that's how it
works
you get dopamine from picking up your
phone but you also get dopamine from
having wonderful conversations you get
you get dopamine from what isn't
dopamine like the reward chemical yes
it's very misunderstood like in like
common terms but a root it is the reward
he good yeah
like checking something off your list
like oh I did that thing or I got that
thing like I posted that thing and I got
this from posting that I did good is it
that sort of yeah it's your brains way
of rewarding you for doing something
that would increase survival chances so
like eating dopamine right all these
things like sex
dopamine yes like all these things I
feel really good yes and we've been
evolutionary like designed to if these
things are happening to you and must
mean you're doing pretty good because a
lot of people have just died like I mean
took us a while to have a sustainable
culture to where we don't have to worry
about just surviving it's like you're
doing good you're getting that dopamine
good that's what you want is to stay
safe and like polios or penicillins less
than a hundred years old so as people
from just like dying from everything
very long like you two people ago you
people to go but Oh with a lot of people
have ADHD as well from the phone I
really believe because that dopamine so
all adderall does increase your dopamine
levels which inherently allows you to
focus because the lack of dopamine
people or the brain is set up to seek
novelty to feel stimulated right that's
why I like if you get into something
like music's really good example you can
like the real-life hoppy stuff in like
four years you're listening to like
underground music that's got like 400
followers and he's doing out of the
basement like so you will always go more
and more and more and more mm-hmm and
this constant like blasts of dopamine
makes it incredibly hard to focus when
things are more mundane than that and
it's so it's just so much input that
just sitting seems hard alright it's
super hard to focus and it's the that's
the thing it's so hard to focus because
we're used to you know we kind of when
we're online we kind of let our minds
rip you don't have to focus you can look
over there's an app there's not oh
there's this person unlike that one not
quick you we kind of let it rip I feel
like sometimes the ADHD brain is kind of
trained by just the nature of phones
yeah even on a neurochemical level I
think it's incredibly enhance just
because you now live in a heightened
state of dopamine go to your phone and
then you sit down to read not as
stimulating not colorful not loud it's
not so novel right it's very very hard
well in sit and so that's the thing is
finding things that you're interested in
that are gossip and what so-and-so is
doing and you know that's why we've got
to be finding things that were
interested in that aren't just negative
to us so and so what I mean by that is
something that's stimulating so if
you're sitting through a lecture of
something about music and you love music
you're gonna be paying attention you're
being tentative but if you're not
interested in music at all you're not
going to be paying attention so finding
something that stimulates you other than
gossip and
passing the time and I feel like we have
really gotten the short side of this
when it comes to all our hobbies need to
be lucrative in general so a lot of them
are very vain very shallow okay like
talking about big concepts and being
real interested and like a lot of these
things that don't make a lot of money is
not very culturally supported they're
just being sold things right all the
time well we're always thinking about
the right now right right we're thinking
of how do we get this right now the
soonest how do we enjoy our life for the
long run and you really feel or see
people like I really wish that uh people
didn't shame each other for stuff that
they like general because it's like you
get the stereotypical like a young
person like male or female I think you
probably guess what they're into more
than likely like what the 80% accuracy I
think as we just saw are kind of like
this homogenized like this is what's
culturally cool there's not a lot of
introduction to a lot of like other
other things that could be really
enriching I think it's a it's a big
problem yeah it's crazy though
so much I mean it's it's nice that just
this conversation I'm thinking they're
just looping back like everything we're
talking about you flew back to ego to
being mindful these is such important
concepts it really is such an anchor for
everything we've talked about I really
think because like you people you know I
would say there's nothing more
disappointing than meeting someone
they're exactly who you think they are
just like really normal in like that
heteronormativity is like so championed
right you just got to be normal everyone
wants to be normal
yeah I was very boring it really is
boring to us too yes and we noticed that
within ourselves and within each other
we know when we're not being our
authentic selves we feel it our ego
reacts to it and we know when other
people aren't being either
it puts this weird non trusting in our
conversation I really think that uh well
even like Netflix like sitcoms are my
favorite example of pacification cuz
it's just like it's so comfy that's just
the most comfy media it's not
challenging which some people can write
I my life is extremely easy like I don't
have a lot of like real actual issues
that I don't cause for myself so like
all my problems are my fault and fully
aware of that so it's probably nice to
come home after like a long day that was
pretty [__] and like watch a sitcom but
that is like just like a baby food for
your brain it is like it's just a some
people also don't really like to
research like that's a personality type
definitely I'd like to be like
challenged in that way and so it's it's
hard for me to empathize with them
because it's like that's all I really
enjoy it's just like new really crunchy
information right we both love the
novelty yeah but then I think that your
personality becomes the office then and
you get this extremely homogenized
person from it right like just from the
media that we consume as young people
like you like this is my sense of humor
we're all under these like pretty bland
things that just like help us pass time
and never really questioned anything or
anything grand but what we don't see is
right right beneath our eyes as we're
doing these things they're becoming who
we are you know if you do the same thing
every day for 30 days whether you want
it to or not it's kind of video art you
know it's it's it's shaping your
personality at least right you're just a
sack of habits chasing three brain
chemicals just a bunch of mush under
there yeah yeah you've got it I mean
there's certain people that you know
there's a growth mindset and a fixed
mindset but I think that the way that
life just inherently is now especially
in the Western culture it's like you
have to realize that if you don't have
an active growth mindset then society
and the internet and your phone is going
to make you into their fixed mindset
they're gonna they're gonna send you on
their wild-goose chase that's gonna be
your interests they're gonna give you an
ego to use
I've got a lot of really hard Chris it
was criticisms of capitalism in general
I really think that uh like the growth
mindset is even misconstrued because of
it because it's like monetary gain is
what's prized here like that's that's
what we flex you know you wear the
change you drive the car and the so I am
like all of our like economic system is
based around consuming and then being
what you have mm-hmm that's uh one of my
favorite things is you climb up the
corporate ladder you get to the top you
realize you're on the wrong building
yeah I like that it's just uh and it's
incredibly predatory you see when you
pick up your phone - I'm never just
trying to sell you stuff make you feel
bad and I think that like that model
just like constantly like you just start
selling your time and buying stuff like
that sir here be quiet don't make noise
sell your time and buy stuff like that's
the loop in that growth mindset can be
very much so sold to people through like
a lot of self-help books to just make
you make more money to bring more stuff
right right
it's a sucks man it's I mean I think
it's worth talking about though it's
worth having these conversations and
it's worth trying to teach people and
trying to make sure people know it's
like hey I'm not trying to judge you I'm
not trying to like tell you you know
that you're that I'm better than you in
any way it's like I'm trying to to make
you realize that your attention is being
sold to you I'm trying to make you
realize that what you care about
throughout your life should not should
be your own decision and it shouldn't be
your primitive chemicals being used
against you which is the world that
we're living and it's creating way too
much divided and on it just causes this
sense of uh well it's a lack it's not
fulfilling at all I mean you buy a new
car you like it for two months then you
stop washing it it's just like how you
get to work yeah like this thing that
you work so hard for
it's just but a little bit of
satisfaction this is what's next what's
next
like I feel like a lot of depression
anxiety come from systemic reasons
mm-hmm that we just are like a thrust
into this world you're just like here to
make money man
just here to work we're not here for
that that's something it's like sure you
got to play that game we've got a
culture as a real thing societies a real
thing you gotta exist in this world but
like the essence of who you should be at
the end of every evident of everyday is
just someone who's trying to learn what
this is all about right next to a bunch
of other people trying to learn what
this is all about and that harkens back
to the ego too because selling you stuff
is so ego pandering it is I fought for I
mean I have I've had a massive ego in
the past like want the nicest car want
just big muscles and I want everyone to
think I'm smart and funny and huge
totally and whatever I could buy to make
that happen I would whatever like
attention I could get just from monetary
purchases 100 percent would do that and
it's really hard to not be like that
because we've just been raised in a
culture that that's that's just how it
is but but so here's the thing as the
jump that was always something that I
could understand at the moment I was
introspective about it later is in the
moment you don't realize you are doing
these things right like you're like that
what are you talking about I'm just this
is who I am I'm just buying these things
that I like I'm just doing these things
but what we're saying is the essence of
why you're doing these things is your
ego you know that's what your ego is you
just mean you don't have to bow to it
this is actually unintentionally been an
excellent podcast about you go cool yeah
I like podcasts dude I feel like the the
essence of ego it's actually confusing
concept I told you I've I've been like
I've been doing so much research around
the word ego because I feel like I in my
head I want to be able to explain it in
like two sentences to people but I'm not
there yet by any means so I think that I
mean you you'll be on this podcast not
in any way and we're going to have these
more conversations in depth about ego
and I mean we talked about mindfulness
and all these things that loop together
I think over time that listeners will
really have a great grasp on
Iko and why it's important to understand
and I don't know if it's just what we
chose to talk about all pander to the
ego or if everything I call the human
decisions you make really revert back to
that I would like to keep an eye on that
so we can't wait to talk yeah yeah
because when you keep floating I mean in
what happens in conversations we keep
floating above ego and keep floating
like the better you get and you kind of
go this meta above the conversation like
we're two of course we both still have
egos but we're creating this that's
Terry Parker definitely pretty big at
some point of times yeah I am extremely
at my core pretty argumentative love to
be this market I like to be right I
don't want to be the strong one like it
definitely just want to be that guy like
like at my being that's this is just how
I've always been
so trying to release that it's been
pretty hard just in general like it's
always like not like oh no I lost it
it's like every day you gotta it's when
you notice that it's your natural state
I was like I'll be Marcus he always
talks about he always he calls himself a
monster and he's like dude am I being a
monster like I gotta push these things
out I gotta I gotta attack I'm like I
know that like I have these things but
they're not always productive to my
conversation and I was productive to
what brings me forth or lives I feel
like you'll definitely see come to them
more than once and okay I really want
like a people any listener is gonna
really start to delve into this if you
fail that's part of it you're gonna fail
for the rest of your life that's just
how it is like you're gonna fail
sometimes and that is more than
acceptable and you just have to take
note of it be better yeah
you're not failure just as much as
you're not your ego you know these other
things we're talking about you're also
not failure you just got a restart the
next day and that's the thing is it's
not like oh I failed now I got to redo
it it's like no you never really fail if
you think about it it's just like oh
well I didn't get to where I wanted to
be today tomorrow no doubt in my mind
I'm gonna start that same thing I'm
gonna do that same thing I'm gonna pick
up where I left off so what do we what
do we learn today kind of thing ya know
I failed the day and I could beat myself
up like actually journaling is really
helpful
- Thank You Man I'm a huge advocate of
journaling scribing it's definitely
important I don't do it enough mm-hmm
but it's definitely really helpful
because then you can see progress - you
go back like two months you look at what
you're writing about that's something
that I like looking back at my notes I'm
getting there now it's some sort of
weird block that I have I have like I
have so much work that needs to be oh
here's the rough draft let's go sketch
it out and make it a final reading back
my journal or reading back my thoughts
but it is important it's something that
I'm also working on so so to work on all
these things
journaling definitely helps mindfulness
meditation there's plenty of apps
I mean you search the word mindfulness
meditation anywhere nowadays you just
follow the directions I promise it will
help with with with ego with seeing
people as other with your emotions
getting out of control with with all
these these concepts mindfulness
meditation even not even you even
necessarily have to meditate but the
incessant study of these things is
helpful oh absolutely what is that
because it just allows you to actually
see what's happening I will say that
I've taken like pretty long breaks after
starting meditating and then falling off
and then get back on it and by emotional
state is so much more varied I don't
meditate like my I find myself being
reactive much more so than I normally
would be if I was meditating
consistently do you notice it in the
moment like oh [__] like two minutes ago
I just did that or do you notice it you
know say like oh I meditated this week I
noticed last week I kind of wasn't sure
cut
is it is it it retrospectively or it's
it depends how long I've meditated for
like I took probably meditate for like
six weeks and by the end of it I just
kind of found myself back on my [__]
really doing all the stuff like oh just
my habits just doing my habits
mindlessly like a careening through days
looking at my phone not taking note of
things and just like not living now and
at all to any meaningful degree and it
really detracted from like my day-to-day
experience right there's a saying that I
really like that Albert Marcus says hit
me with it
today's a good day to die
do you think I'd like if you just live
in a way that you be content with I mean
I lived I lived I laughed I danced I
played today yeah a good day I think
that if I died today that'd be except
like I lived my life to the utmost
potential today right yeah don't put all
like that oh I have done everything I've
wanted to in this life and I'm good to
die now it's not like that it's just
today in this moment I'm being what I
can be I have done what I can do today
and I don't want to misconstrue that
with like being physically productive
like how I checked on my list off so
just like enjoying the intricacies of
conversation and laughing and letting
yourself just just genuinely enjoying
every second did you slow down did you
did you you know maybe take a breath
outside just one second extra longer and
breathing in like man I'm so grateful
for my backyard I'm grateful for me yeah
I think gratitude definitely helps like
the a good day to die today it's
definitely like you need gratitude to be
able to feel grateful for today being
that good day most certainly I've got a
I'm very lucky I've got a very excellent
family dynamic I sold my parents they're
just very good people I walked on my
house about 2:00 a.m. one night and I
was like I'm so thankful that this is a
place of like happiness for me like I
know that many people walk in their
house and the source of pain I like to
think about your safest space being like
a place of discomfort to any real degree
it's just so unfortunate enough like
there's a very very gracious of it yeah
like that yeah that's you know that that
sparked something in me that's I'm very
grateful of my space here as well it's
just cool to see you know you're someone
who I've you know I had a riddled
upbringing you know and you're someone
who like you know we talked about
multiple times today like you've you've
had a great you know you say you've had
your own experiences of course just as
anybody has but to know that you're
still grateful for like having a home
you know cuz there's I'm so grateful for
what I have here but for me I'm so
grateful because there was you know many
years of my childhood to where I was
my feet were in the air I was homeless
you know was like it didn't have a
consistent that place and so man I just
I just want to say
thanks for being grateful in your own
life because it just is like I think
it's so important that you're taking
time to be grateful for what you have
and not being you know greedy about
because there's plenty of people who
greedy is not the right word
there's plenty people who just aren't
grateful for what they have and there's
a lot of people who would love to have
anything that they have and that's such
a close a thing they hear all the time
but it's it's important to your life
it's not you owe this person you should
be grateful because this person has left
it's like it has less it's it's it's a
gratitude that you gave to your life you
were really just cheating yourself by
not being grateful for where I have to
be honest because it really doesn't
affect anyone else but you mm-hmm for
the most part like if you just are
constantly and one if you're not
grateful you live in a constant state of
discontent that's very unfortunate
because then you will seek outside
sources for contentment you'll never be
grateful for it I was a I was at lunch
with like a multi-millionaire gym owner
for like a business lunch and his kid
was there with him he's probably like 14
I was about 18 and we were on the water
on the East Coast and he was complaining
to his father that uh their yachts not
big enough and at that moment
wow what a sentence that's insane this
is madness right well it's the thing
about it though is that kid you know he
was eight or no you were 18 he was to
what 14 years probably sophomore your
husband
it was nothing is he's not he's not born
like he just knows all this language he
knows gratitude he knows all these
things like he knows about yachts I mean
he needs to be taught these things like
you have to be able to take a second and
slow down and he needs to have I have a
way of that being talked to him you know
these are things that as parents it's
important for us to do like you need to
show your kid why they're grateful for
what they have
it's a tenant of Stoicism to go live
with the poor for a few days
right get in touch with the people it's
probably honestly important it's
probably great I mean I know Megan went
over to
South Africa Ghana I think if she was
there and helped out and taught it like
a school and stuff remote she came back
she's like man it's obviously eye
opening you know that that's a pretty
profound way to go about it but seeing
people with less it definitely makes you
grateful for what you have and I love I
love them people go to Africa I've never
been but when they come back and they're
like everyone was so happy there they're
just so grateful for everything or in
weird content with not much not much
that's why stuffs doesn't matter like
stuff is not important stuff sex stuff
is definitely perishable and you will
get over it but if you can find like the
wherewithal to just accept what it is or
like who you are or what's happening
around you and just like genuinely
taking the good parts and enjoy them
right you're just gonna constantly be
sad be discontent yeah and I see that
with body issues a lot so I'm a personal
trainer and if people you can't you
gotta enjoy the process like if you
you're like I will be happy when I get
here you're never gonna be happy because
when you get there you want more but if
you can find it in your being to accept
yourself now you will be content the
whole way yeah you can't put your
happiness in the outcome because you
don't control the outcome I've heard
that analogy with tennis players so like
I will only be happy like Serena
Williams I'm only gonna be happy and
proud of myself
if I win but you don't have control over
that if this person is more physically
and if they're better at this game or
whatever happens and they win this game
that's you can't control that
what we can do is you can be present and
you can go give it your all and you can
you can you can be content with the
outcome that you gave your 100% whether
you won or lost and if you have the
first mindset who does it hurt
ultimately it doesn't change the outcome
if you lose and you were only gonna be
happy if you want your you're the only
one suffering from it right so we really
just create our own torment just some
degree we create order we create our own
fear and then we get into a boxing ring
then we try to box it
I really think the I really don't like
capitalism then we're gonna people are
definitely gonna find that out well I
mean because it's a come on comrades
it's the winning the winning mindset got
ya right thinks there's no it's all
about efficiency no time to live now I
gotta live tomorrow I gotta do all these
things mm-hmm and that's just not what's
the point of that what's the what we
don't get to the end do you think you
don't get to the end like all right well
at one see you later
good night I'm gonna go die just go do
stuff for other people yeah your life is
in between you just end up and if you're
really good at it upon a pile of gold
alone realizing you didn't cherish a
single moment because you're not in that
rat race I'd rather what's the saying
Mike stud had a lyric I'd rather be
broke than rich alone I always like I
wanted scrooge mcduck on the pile of
gold sad man
okay sad van scrooge mcduck well Spencer
let's uh let's round it out is there
anything that you want to go over one
more time for listeners
let's take a look definitely take a look
I'll just live like today's a good day
to die
wavelength today is a good day to that
I'm just like really think about that
enjoy the present moment as much as you
can
yeah I agree man it's very important
Spencer Hicks I love you so much man
I'm glad I be on the podcast I'm glad to
have you a million times more I hope
thanks for your friendship in your
conversation and your enlightening words
too if you enjoy that podcast go ahead
and give it a like give me a follow
whatever you got to do on the social
media thing and make sure to send it to
a friend if there's somebody in your
life that you think would benefit from
any of the things that we discussed in
this podcast and of course pay attention
to what whatever app you're using
they're gonna I don't play some song or
podcast or a YouTube video next so just
be wary of your day be conscious stay
mindful have a good day check our love
podcast out
you